<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Algebraic K-Theory on Exploring mathematics</title>
        <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/algebraic-k-theory/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Algebraic K-Theory on Exploring mathematics</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/algebraic-k-theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Wall&#39;s finiteness obstruction</title>
        <link>http://localhost:1313/p/walls-finiteness-obstruction/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://localhost:1313/p/walls-finiteness-obstruction/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="http://localhost:1313/p/walls-finiteness-obstruction/images/Wall-finiteness.png" alt="Featured image of post Wall&#39;s finiteness obstruction" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a long time, I have been interested in $K$-theory. I am no expert, and I have not really been focusing on &amp;ldquo;learning all the hands-on K-theory there is&amp;rdquo;. However, I think bundles are cool, and $K$-theory has been a recurring theme throughout my mathematical journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I read (and did not understand) some notes on topological $K$-theory in my second year, and when I wrote a bachelors thesis on $C^*$-algebras and non-commutative tori, it showed up as a topological tool, which is surprisingly useful in the world of operator algebras. During my master years, I was getting interested in stable and chromatic homotopy theory, and when I wrote my master thesis on differential- and Hodge-filtered cohomology theories, $K$-theory followed me to give cool examples of beautiful maths and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether it was topological $K$-theory, operator $K$-theory, Karoubis Multiplicative $K$-theory, or even Morava $K$-theory, I felt $K$-theory was something I &amp;ldquo;knew something about&amp;rdquo;. However, algebraic $K$-theory is a beast I never dared to learn more about. Why? Well, it is immensly difficult to compute, all the &amp;ldquo;basic theory&amp;rdquo; (of $K_0, K_1, K_2$, for example) can become quite technical and algebraic, as well as extremely messy (yes, I am looking at you, $K_2$). I mean, operator and topological $K$-theory can also be hard, but then you only need to deal with two things, $K_0$ and $K_1$, due to Bott periodicity, which is not possible for algebraic $K$-theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, something has changed (probably starting a PhD, lol), and I just embarked on learning Algebraic $K$-theory.
I will try to skim through some constructions, as well as some motivation in this blogpost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-serre-swan-theorem-and-k_0-theory&#34;&gt;The Serre-Swan theorem and $K_0$-theory&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most beautiful theorems in math, at least in my opinion, is the Serre-Swan theorem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem: (Serre-Swan)&lt;/strong&gt;
Let $X$ be a compact Hausdorff space, and $C(X)$ the ring of continuous $\mathbb{R}$-valued functions.
The globals sections functor $\Gamma: \operatorname{VBun}(X) \to \operatorname{fgproj}(C(X))$ from the category of vector bundles on $X$ to the category of finitely generated modules over $C(X)$ is an equivalence of categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, this theorem is amazing. It gives a bridge between geometry and topology, allowing us to define topological versions of $K$-theory on one side, and algebraic versions of $K$-theory on the other. Note for example that the objects $C(X)$ are precisely the &lt;em&gt;commutative&lt;/em&gt; $C^* $-algebras. For an arbitrary $C^*$-algebra $A$, one can think of the category $\operatorname{fgproj}(A)$ as &amp;ldquo;noncommutative vector bundles on $A$&amp;rdquo;. This is precisely the idea that lets us define operator $K$-theory as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One reasonable question however, is &amp;ldquo;why finitely generated and projective&amp;rdquo;?
Intuitively, finitely generated comes from the fact that we work with finitely dimensional vector bundles, so the &amp;ldquo;bases&amp;rdquo; correspond to &amp;ldquo;generators&amp;rdquo;. The projective part is maybe more interesting.
Over nice spaces, one can show that if $F \to X$ is a sub-bundle of $E \to X$, then $F$ is a direct summand in $E$. By certain lemmas, we can realize that all bundles $F$ are summands in the trivial bundles. This is a fact on the topological side of the Serre-Swan theorem. On the algebraic side, this amounts to bundles giving modules which are summands in free modules. Those are precisely the projectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyways, let&amp;rsquo;s get back to algebraic $K$-theory. Studying isomorphism classes of finitely projective modules only gives us a monoid under direct sum. If we want an abelian group, we have to group complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Definition: $K_0(R)$&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let $R$ be a ring and $\mathbf{P}(R)$ denote the monoid of isomorphism classes of finitely generated projective $R$-modules.
Then we define the $K$-theory of $R$ as the group completion $K_0(R) = \mathbf{P}(R)^{grp}$.
This is contravariantly functorial as a map $R \to S$ lets us define a $R$-module from an $S$-module, giving a map $K_0(S) \to K_0(R)$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that we can define $K_0$ of not only rings, but other objects as well.
For symmetric monoidal categories, this is essentally the same construction as above.
$K$-theory of abelian (and more generally exact) categories amount to defining $K_0(\mathcal{A})$ to be the free abelian group on objects of $\mathcal{A}$ subject to the relations that $[A] = [A&amp;rsquo;]+[A&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;]$ if there exists a short exact sequences
$$0 \to A&amp;rsquo; \to A \to A&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; \to 0.$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can of course ask if we can take $K_0(Mod R)$ for some $R$, but there are size-issues regarding this. If we try, we will just obtain $K_0(Mod R) = 0$, by the Eilenberg Swindle. However, in nice situations (if R is noetherian, for example), we can consider the category of finitely generated modules, which under group completion yields what we call $G_0$-theory.
If the ring $R$ is also regular, then $K_0(R) = G_0(R)$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;walls-finiteness-obstruction&#34;&gt;Wall&amp;rsquo;s finiteness obstruction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will not try to write a textbook on $K$-theory here, but rather explore some interesting facts.
To do that, let us first ask the following question:
If $M$ is a nice space, say a compact manifold, does $M$ have the homotopy type of a finite CW-complex?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In special cases, we can answer this question immediately. For example, if $M$ is smooth, it can be triangulated, and thus it is even homeomorphic to a finite CW-complex. In the general case, it is hard. We know that $M$ has the homotopy type of a CW-complex (call it $X$), so it is sufficient to figure out if $X$ has the homotopy type of a &lt;em&gt;finite&lt;/em&gt; CW-complex.
We do not a priori know any finiteness conditions, but we may hope that some information about this homotopical question can be found in the homotopy groups of $X$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, for a group $G$, we can consider the group ring $\mathbb{Z}[G]$. By the augmentation map, defined by sending all of $G$ to $1$, we get a surjective map $\varepsilon: \mathbb{Z}[G] \to \mathbb{Z}$, which splits as $\mathbb{Z}$ is a projective abelian group. On $K$-theory, we can consider the quotient of $K_0(\mathbb{Z}[G])$ by $K_0(\mathbb{Z}) = \mathbb{Z}$. This defines the zeroth Whitehead group, $Wh_0(G)$.
If we apply this to $G = \pi_1(X)$ for some CW-complex $X$ as above, then we can, with some extra assumption, obtain an obstruction to $X$ being homotopy equivalent to a finite CW-complex!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Definition: (Finitely dominated CW-complexes)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A CW-complex $X$ is &lt;em&gt;dominated&lt;/em&gt; by a CW-complex $K$ if $X$ is a retract of $K$.
That is, there are maps
$$X \to K \to X$$ that compose to the identity on $X$ (up to homotopy).
We say $X$ is &lt;em&gt;finitely dominated&lt;/em&gt; if there exist a finite CW-complex $K$ such that $X$ is dominated by $K$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since finitely dominated complexes are retracts of the finite CW-complexes, we can note that the finitely dominated complexes correspond precisely to the compact objects in the $\infty$-category of spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem: (Wall&amp;rsquo;s finiteness obstruction)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assume a CW-complex $X$ is finitely dominated. Then, there exists an element $w(X) \in Wh_0(\pi_1(G))$ such that
$w(X) = 0$ if and only if $X$ is homotopy equivalent to a finite CW-complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just the existence of it can be used to give a new class of spaces that have the homotopy type of a finite CW-complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corollary:&lt;/strong&gt;
Let $X$ be a finitely dominated space which is simply connected. Then $X$ has the homotopy type of a finite CW-complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proof:&lt;/em&gt;
This boils down to
$$w(X) \in Wh_0(\pi_1(X)) = Wh_0(pt) = K_0(\mathbb{Z}[pt])/K_0(\mathbb{Z}) = 0.$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-image-of-w--in-wh_0g&#34;&gt;The image of $w(-)$ in $Wh_0(G)$&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the examples of fintely dominated spaces I can come up with on the spot, will certainly be finite CW-complexes, so I&amp;rsquo;m tempted to ask how &amp;ldquo;non-trivial&amp;rdquo; $w(-)$ really is.
That is, if we are given a class $[P]$ in $Wh_0(G) = K_0(\mathbb{Z}[G])/K_0(\mathbb{Z})$, can we find a finitely dominated CW-complex $X$ such that $w(x) = [P]$?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-wx-more-explicit&#34;&gt;Making $w(X)$ more explicit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;todo-show-lurie-remark-23-that-all-for-g-finitely-presented-all-of-wh_0zg-arises-as-wx-for-some-x&#34;&gt;Todo Show (Lurie remark 23) that all for G finitely presented, all of Wh_0(ZG) arises as w(X) for some X.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given some cohomological bound on $X$, which is automatic for finitely dominated spaces, then we can explicitly define $w(X)$ in terms of computable pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recall that a sheaf $\mathcal{L}$ of abelian groups is a local system of abelian groups if it is locally constant. That is, if each point has an open neighborhood $U$ such that $\mathcal{L}|_U$ is isomorphic to a sheafification of a constant presheaf. Sheaf cohomology yields a way to take cohomology with coefficients in a local system.
The reason we care is the following theorem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem: (Representations of fundamental groups and local systems)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The category of representations of $\pi_1(X)$ is equivalent to the category of local systems on $X$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;todo-how-does-this-depend-on-x&#34;&gt;TODO how does this depend on x?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gives us a way to characterize finitely dominated spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem: (Characterization of finitely dominated spaces)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A space $X$ is finitely dominated if and only if the following conditions hold:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\pi_0(X)$ is a finite set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\pi_1(X,x)$ is a finitely presented group for each $x \in X$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each $x \in X$, let $X_x^o$ denote the path component of $x$, let $V$ be a representation of $\pi_1(X,x)$ (which corresponds to a local system). The assignment $V \mapsto H^k(X^o; V)$ commutes with filtered directed colimits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the setup above, there exist an integer $n$ such that for any representation $V$ of $\pi_1(X,x)$, $H^k(X^o; V) = 0$ for $k &amp;gt; n$.
In this case, we say $X$ has homotopy dimension $\leq n$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;explain-an-idea-for-computing-it&#34;&gt;Explain an idea for computing it&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We obtain the following explicit way to view $w(X)$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem: (Explicit formula for $w(X)$)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let $X$ be a finitely dominated space, and make the following choices:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose an integer $n \geq 2$ such that $X$ has homotopy dimension $\leq n$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose a CW-complex $Z$ of dimension $&amp;lt;n$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose a $(n-1)$-connected map $f: Z \to X$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, $H_n(X,Z; \mathbb{Z}[G])$ is a finitely generated projective $\mathbb{Z}[G]$-module, and $w(X)$ is the class
$$w(X) = (-1)^n [H_n(X,Z; \mathbb{Z}[G])] \in Wh_0(\mathbb{Z}[G]).$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;todo-and-what-is-this-rep-cohom-wrt-uct&#34;&gt;TODO and what is this rep-cohom wrt. UCT?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;todo-do-an-explicit-computation-with-this-formula&#34;&gt;TODO do an explicit computation with this formula&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/splasher.jpg&#34;
	
	
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;The subtitle?&#34;
	
	
&gt;
&lt;em&gt;text&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OnvQggy3Ezw&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;this amazing video&lt;/a&gt; on freediving!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
