<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Spectral sequences on Exploring mathematics</title>
    <link>https://eka2499.github.io/tags/spectral-sequences/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Spectral sequences on Exploring mathematics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://eka2499.github.io/tags/spectral-sequences/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Spectral sequences and multicomplexes - Part III</title>
      <link>https://eka2499.github.io/p/spectral-sequences-and-multicomplexes-part-iii/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eka2499.github.io/p/spectral-sequences-and-multicomplexes-part-iii/</guid>
      <description>As promised when we started the series on spectral sequences and multicomplexes, we aimed at understanding the main results of a master thesis. Finally, I&amp;rsquo;ve had the time to finish this post. I enjoyed writing it quite a lot, but I have been busy with other things, such as acting for Realfagsrevyen and doing project work for other courses. Now that these things are more-or-less out of the way (for now), I finally managed to finish this post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spectral sequences and multicomplexes - Part II</title>
      <link>https://eka2499.github.io/p/spectral-sequences-and-multicomplexes-part-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eka2499.github.io/p/spectral-sequences-and-multicomplexes-part-ii/</guid>
      <description>Welcome back! In the previous post, we took a brief look at spectral sequences and how we could get them from filtered complexes. In this post, we will sketch the main ideas in a proof of the convergence of the Leray-Serre (LS) spectral sequence using techiques from homotopy theory, explore spectral sequences through exact couples and compute an example.
Originally, I planned to spend more time understanding exact couples and head towards the Adams spectral sequence, but as my friend Torgeir recently wrote a great post on this for his dive into (stable) homotopy theory, we&amp;rsquo;ll just briefly touch on the topic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spectral sequences and multicomplexes - Part I</title>
      <link>https://eka2499.github.io/p/spectral-sequences-and-multicomplexes-part-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eka2499.github.io/p/spectral-sequences-and-multicomplexes-part-i/</guid>
      <description>A year ago, I took a course on algebraic topology at NTNU where we covered some homotopy theory, spectral sequences, bundle theory and characteristic classes. Most of the topics stuck with me, and I have been exploring them a bit after the course. The part on spectral sequences grew on me, and at the end of the course, that part fascinated me the most, as they give a puzzle-style way of computing homology and cohomology.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
